[Speaker 1] Okay. I'm not pretty sure because I've never been to one or already, but I would
[المتحدث 1] حسناً. لست متأكداً تماماً لأنني لم أذهب إلى هناك من قبل أو ربما ذهبت بالفعل، لكنني سأحاول
try to get some help out of someone, right? That could help me because I'm an elderly person. So
الحصول على بعض المساعدة من شخص ما، أليس كذلك؟ شخص يمكنه مساعدتي لأنني شخص متقدم في السن. لذا
[Speaker 1] it's, things are more difficult for us than to a young person. So I would.
[المتحدث 1] الأمور تكون أصعب علينا مقارنة بالشخص الشاب. لذا سأفعل ذلك.
[Speaker 2] We call for help. You would call someone on your phone where we could call out for help.
[المتحدث 2] سنطلب المساعدة. ستتصل بشخص ما على هاتفك أو يمكننا طلب المساعدة بصوت عالٍ.
[Speaker 1] Yeah. Yeah. If that was a situation, I call for help actually. Yeah.
[المتحدث 1] نعم. نعم. لو كان هذا هو الموقف، سأطلب المساعدة بالفعل. نعم.
Well, you can say help. Help just to get me out of the flood.
حسناً، يمكنك أن تقول "النجدة". "النجدة، فقط أخرجوني من هذا الفيضان."
[Speaker 1] You know, the thing is like, it's like static in there because that's a tunnel and it has,
[المتحدث 1] كما تعلم، الأمر أشبه بأن يكون هناك ركود في الداخل لأنه نفق وبه،
at the very end of it, it has to like higher points. So the flood comes right in between
في نهايته القصوى، نقاط مرتفعة. لذا يأتي الفيضان مباشرة بينهما
[Speaker 1] into the tunnel and out the tunnel. [Speaker 2] It's like a pool of water.
[المتحدث 1] إلى داخل النفق ثم يخرج من النفق. [المتحدث 2] إنه مثل بركة ماء.
[Speaker 1] Yeah. It wasn't like a pool that you can actually go and swim. Yeah. I will have hope. I will ask
[المتحدث 1] نعم. لم يكن الأمر كبركة يمكنك الذهاب إليها والسباحة فيها بالفعل. نعم. سأحتفظ بالأمل. سأطلب
for help actually. That's what I would do, you know, or maybe if I can, if I cannot find help,
المساعدة بالفعل. هذا ما سأفعله، كما تعلم، أو ربما إذا لم أتمكن من إيجاد مساعدة،
[Speaker 1] I will start running and trying to grab things around me so I'm not to get, you know, in the
[المتحدث 1] سأبدأ في الركض ومحاولة الإمساك بالأشياء من حولي حتى لا أقع، كما تعلم، في
flood and try to escape from there. [Speaker 2] If it flooded, I would swim because I know how to swim,
الفيضان وأحاول الهروب من هناك. [المتحدث 2] لو فاض الماء، لكنت سأسبح لأنني أعرف كيف أسبح،
but do you know how to swim? [Speaker 1] Just a little bit. I get cramps whenever I try to swim, so
ولكن هل تعرف كيف تسبح؟ [المتحدث 1] قليلاً فقط. تصيبني تشنجات كلما حاولت السباحة، لذا
I'm not trying to do so because that comes terrible. [Speaker 2] If you don't have to, you wouldn't try.
أنا لا أحاول فعل ذلك لأن الأمر يصبح فظيعاً. [المتحدث 2] إذا لم تكن مضطراً، فلن تحاول.
[Speaker 1] Yeah. And especially the water, the flood, I mean, it's kind of nasty in that part.
[المتحدث 1] نعم. وخاصة الماء، الفيضان، أعني، إنه نوعاً ما قذر في ذلك الجزء.
All the people from some parts of the city, they are thrown to that part. So I don't,
جميع الناس من بعض أنحاء المدينة، يُلقون (بمخلفاتهم) في ذلك الجزء. لذا أنا لا،
[Speaker 1] it's not recommendable. [Speaker 2] I think a better hypothetical situation would be to be in a
[المتحدث 1] لا يُنصح بذلك. [المتحدث 2] أعتقد أن وضعاً افتراضياً أفضل سيكون أن تكون في مكان جيد
good place with your family, someplace where you're safe and just going to get food to eat.
مع عائلتك، مكان ما آمن وتذهب فقط للحصول على طعام لتأكله.
[Speaker 2] That sounds like the perfect hypothetical situation.
[المتحدث 2] يبدو هذا هو الوضع الافتراضي المثالي.
[Speaker 1] Yeah, I wish I could be safer than that.
[المتحدث 1] نعم، أتمنى لو كنت أكثر أماناً من ذلك.
[Speaker 2] Here's a question here. We've looked at some general conversation starters
[المتحدث 2] إليك سؤال هنا. لقد نظرنا في بعض مفاتيح الحوار العامة
and hypothetical questions. Let's try to connect these to your own thoughts
والأسئلة الافتراضية. دعنا نحاول ربط هذه بأفكارك الخاصة
[Speaker 2] and potential conversations, things that you'd like to talk about.
[المتحدث 2] والمحادثات المحتملة، الأشياء التي تود التحدث عنها.
So we can look back at these conversation starters that we've had and the hypothetical
لذا يمكننا أن نعود إلى مفاتيح الحوار هذه التي أجريناها والأسئلة الافتراضية
[Speaker 2] questions and try to think about the most interesting types of questions and how we
[المتحدث 2] ونحاول التفكير في أكثر أنواع الأسئلة إثارة للاهتمام وكيف يمكننا
might answer another one in a real conversation. What type of situations would you use these types
الإجابة على سؤال آخر في محادثة حقيقية. في أي نوع من المواقف ستستخدم هذه الأنواع
[Speaker 2] of questions? Let's try to categorize this a little bit more. Previously, I showed you a list
[المتحدث 2] من الأسئلة؟ دعنا نحاول تصنيف هذا بشكل أكبر قليلاً. سابقاً، عرضت عليك قائمة
here of these different questions. The first question says, what's the most interesting
هنا بهذه الأسئلة المختلفة. السؤال الأول يقول، "ما هو أكثر مكان مثير للاهتمام
[Speaker 2] place you've ever visited and what made it special? If you answered that question there,
[المتحدث 2] زرته على الإطلاق وما الذي جعله مميزاً؟" إذا أجبت على هذا السؤال هناك،
when would you ask this question in a conversation? [Speaker 1] What kind of situation?
متى ستطرح هذا السؤال في محادثة؟ [المتحدث 1] في أي نوع من المواقف؟
Well, I would like to ask somebody that I recently met. We start a conversation
حسناً، أود أن أسأل شخصاً قابلته مؤخراً. نبدأ محادثة
[Speaker 1] just like an icebreaking thing, right? And just to break the ice, I would start a conversation
[المتحدث 1] تماماً كشيء لكسر الحاجز، أليس كذلك؟ وفقط لكسر الحاجز، سأبدأ محادثة
telling, well, if I see that they're interested in that type of conversation.
أقول فيها، حسناً، إذا رأيت أنهم مهتمون بهذا النوع من المحادثات.
[Speaker 1] But, you know, it's like a very common thing to do, to talk about yourself when you're being
[المتحدث 1] ولكن، كما تعلم، من الشائع جداً أن تتحدث عن نفسك عندما يتم تقديمك
introduced or introducing yourself to somebody, right? And you're looking for questions or,
أو عندما تقدم نفسك لشخص ما، أليس كذلك؟ وأنت تبحث عن أسئلة أو،
[Speaker 1] you know, history that you can tell. [Speaker 2] It's great to have a question that
[المتحدث 1] كما تعلم، تاريخ يمكنك سرده. [المتحدث 2] من الرائع أن يكون لديك سؤال يمكنك الإجابة عليه
you can answer because then you know what you can say. But it helps the other person,
لأنك حينها تعرف ما يمكنك قوله. ولكنه يساعد الشخص الآخر أيضاً،
[Speaker 2] too, if you can ask them a question like this as well. It makes the conversation go
[المتحدث 2] إذا كان بإمكانك طرح سؤال كهذا عليه أيضاً. يجعل المحادثة تسير
smoother. They go both ways as well. [Speaker 1] Yeah. And especially that question that I answered,
بشكل أكثر سلاسة. الأمر يسير في كلا الاتجاهين أيضاً. [المتحدث 1] نعم. وخاصة ذلك السؤال الذي أجبت عليه،
which is the first one, because, you know, you start talking about your working places,
وهو الأول، لأنه، كما تعلم، تبدأ في التحدث عن أماكن عملك،
[Speaker 1] right? And if they tell me, where have I worked? So I tell them in the airport.
[المتحدث 1] أليس كذلك؟ وإذا سألوني، أين عملت؟ فأخبرهم في المطار.
So they ask me if I got to travel a lot, because being an airport employee,
لذا يسألونني إذا كنت أسافر كثيراً، لأنني موظف في المطار،
[Speaker 1] they start asking things like that. I used to work for a very small airline,
[المتحدث 1] يبدأون في طرح أسئلة من هذا القبيل. كنت أعمل في شركة طيران صغيرة جداً،
right, that works only, flights only locally here within the country. So I used to talk about
صحيح، تعمل فقط، رحلاتها محلية فقط هنا داخل البلاد. لذا كنت أتحدث عن
[Speaker 1] our islands, San Pedro Sula, which is a northern point place here in the country. And that's just
[المتحدث 1] جزرنا، سان بيدرو سولا، وهي مكان في نقطة شمالية هنا في البلاد. وذلك فقط
to break the ice and start a conversation. I usually, or talking about their family,
لكسر الحاجز وبدء محادثة. عادةً ما أتحدث، أو أتحدث عن عائلاتهم،
[Speaker 1] where they're from, and all that kind of stuff. Just to break the ice. That's always the same
[المتحدث 1] من أين هم، وكل تلك الأشياء. فقط لكسر الحاجز. دائماً نفس الشيء.
thing. [Speaker 2] This is something that you're really comfortable with yourself. You've had these
[المتحدث 2] هذا شيء تشعر بالراحة تجاهه حقاً. لقد أجريت هذه المحادثات
conversations a lot in English. So if we need to step outside of the comfort zone a little bit,
كثيراً باللغة الإنجليزية. لذا إذا احتجنا إلى الخروج قليلاً من منطقة الراحة،
[Speaker 2] maybe we could ask another one of these questions. Okay. If you could choose another
[المتحدث 2] ربما يمكننا طرح سؤال آخر من هذه الأسئلة. حسناً. إذا كان بإمكانك اختيار سؤال آخر
question besides the first one, which question would you choose? And when would you ask this
غير السؤال الأول، أي سؤال ستختار؟ ومتى ستطرح هذا السؤال؟
[Speaker 2] question? [Speaker 1] Okay. Let me just read them back again. Tell me about a challenge you overcame.
[المتحدث 2] [المتحدث 1] حسناً. دعني أقرأها مرة أخرى. أخبرني عن تحدٍّ تغلبت عليه.
What did you learn from it? What's something you're looking forward to in the near future?
ماذا تعلمت منه؟ ما هو الشيء الذي تتطلع إليه في المستقبل القريب؟
[Speaker 1] What hobby or activity do you enjoy that others might find surprising? Okay. One of the things
[المتحدث 1] ما هي الهواية أو النشاط الذي تستمتع به وقد يجده الآخرون مفاجئاً؟ حسناً. أحد الأشياء
is just to get a new job. That's one of my challenges, because even if I'm an elderly
هو مجرد الحصول على وظيفة جديدة. هذا أحد تحدياتي، لأنه حتى لو كنت شخصاً متقدماً في السن،
[Speaker 1] person, but I need to support myself. I'm not used to being supported by somebody else.
[المتحدث 1] لكنني بحاجة إلى إعالة نفسي. لست معتاداً على أن يعيلني شخص آخر.
I've always been a provider, so I need to get me a job myself. And it's been hard and challenging
لقد كنت دائماً المعيل، لذا أحتاج إلى الحصول على وظيفة بنفسي. وكان الأمر صعباً ومليئاً بالتحديات
[Speaker 1] to me, because as I told you, I'm an elderly person, and you know, possibilities in my country,
[المتحدث 1] بالنسبة لي، لأنه كما أخبرتك، أنا شخص متقدم في السن، وكما تعلم، الإمكانيات في بلدي،
there are not too many for people like me or somebody else my same age and things like that.
ليست كثيرة جداً لأشخاص مثلي أو لشخص آخر في نفس عمري وأشياء من هذا القبيل.
[Speaker 1] But, you know, the more prepared I am, the faster I'll get a job, right? But even if you study a lot
[المتحدث 1] ولكن، كما تعلم، كلما كنت مستعداً بشكل أفضل، كلما حصلت على وظيفة بشكل أسرع، أليس كذلك؟ ولكن حتى لو درست كثيراً
sometimes and you have a lot of experience, that's not enough in this country, because
في بعض الأحيان ولديك الكثير من الخبرة، فهذا ليس كافياً في هذا البلد، لأن
[Speaker 1] you've got a lot of competition with younger people well prepared for the kind of job that
[المتحدث 1] لديك الكثير من المنافسة مع الشباب المستعدين جيداً لنوع الوظيفة التي قد نتقدم إليها.
we might be applying for. [Speaker 2] I'm really sorry to hear that it's been so challenging.
[المتحدث 2] يؤسفني حقاً أن أسمع أن الأمر كان صعباً للغاية.
I know in many places it's a challenge for elderly people to find equal opportunities.
أعلم أنه في العديد من الأماكن يمثل تحدياً للأشخاص المتقدمين في السن لإيجاد فرص متكافئة.
[Speaker 2] But just after talking with you a few times for a few classes, I can really tell that you have
[المتحدث 2] ولكن بعد التحدث معك عدة مرات في بضع دروس، يمكنني حقاً أن أقول إن لديك
some awesome communication skills. You have some impressive experience. And if I were an employer,
بعض مهارات التواصل الرائعة. لديك بعض الخبرات المثيرة للإعجاب. ولو كنت صاحب عمل،
[Speaker 2] I would really be interested in your resume and your experience. You have a lot of great things
[المتحدث 2] لكنت مهتماً حقاً بسيرتك الذاتية وخبرتك. لديك الكثير من الأشياء الرائعة لتقدمها،
to offer and might have problems finding opportunities in Honduras, but I don't think
وقد تواجه مشاكل في إيجاد فرص في هندوراس، لكنني لا أعتقد
[Speaker 2] you would have any type of problem finding opportunities in other places. I think you
[المتحدث 2] أنك ستواجه أي نوع من المشاكل في إيجاد فرص في أماكن أخرى. أعتقد أنك
do it. You just have to believe in yourself. We have some really wonderful skills and communication
ستفعل ذلك. عليك فقط أن تؤمن بنفسك. لديك بعض المهارات الرائعة حقاً ومهارات التواصل.
[Speaker 2] skills. I'm so impressed by your ability to put things into words.
[المتحدث 2] أنا معجب جداً ببراعتك اللغوية.